

# Mandela Washington Fellowship for Young African Leaders Participant Application: Fetiha Abdella

Application Status: Submitted

## I. General Information

Given Name(s)	Fetiha
Middle Name (Other Name)	Kedir
Surname (Family Name)	Abdella
Date of Birth	12/15/1991
Gender	Female
Marital Status	Married
Citizenship of your spouse	Ethiopia
Are you, or is any member of your immediate family (parents, siblings, spouse, or children) or household, employed by the U.S.Government?	No
I wish to join the YALI Network to access virtual resources and networking opportunities for young African leaders.	Yes

Are you a U.S. Citizen or a U.S. Permanent Resident?	No
Country of Citizenship	Ethiopia
Second Country of Citizenship, if applicable	
Country of Residence	Ethiopia
City or Town of Birth	Addis Ababa
Country of Birth	Ethiopia
Select the location that best describes where you grew up	National capital
Select the location that best describes where you currently live	National capital
Do you have a disability?	No
Have a passport	No

## II. Contact Information

Primary Phone	0933676855
Work Phone	
Mobile Phone	0933676855
Email Address	fetiha191.kedir@gmail.com
Alternate Email Address	

Current Address	24 kebele Addis Ababa Ethiopia
Permanent Address	24 kebele Addis Ababa Ethiopia

## III. Institute Track

First Choice	Leadership in Business
Second Choice	Leadership in Public Management
Third Choice	Leadership in Civic Engagement

# IV. Current Professional and Educational Experience

Are you currently a student?	No
What is your highest level of education?	Bachelors

Are you currently employed?	Self-employed
Do you work full-time or part-time?	Full-time
Job Title	Software developer
Name of your employing organization	Self employeed
City	Addis Ababa
Country	Ethiopia
Choose the category that best describes your organization	Local or National Business
Start date at this employer	june 2017
Number of staff who you supervise	1
Name of your supervisor	Ewnetim Getaneh
Supervisor phone number	0912382747
Supervisor email	ewnget77@gmail.com
Which of the following best describes the topics related to what you are addressing through your professional and volunteer work?	Technology

#### V. Personal Statements

Please give a brief description of your professional background and current work, including any specific professional accomplishments within the last year. Why have you chosen this work?

"Don't wait 30 days and stand inline to make a living, be your own boss!". My dad used to say this when i was growing up. I always knew i wanted to run my own business. Be successful female Entrepreneur

I went to university and got my first degree on computer science .After graduation, i have worked for multiple private organization as software developer and team leader.

Sine 2017, i had involved in two software startups. I was disappointed when the first startup company couldn't workout quite as planned. I took this failure as an opportunity to start another startup which is currently running successfully.

We have developed ranges of products, starting from e-commerce platforms to other business oriented software solutions. we are currently working on mobile games for kids.Our aim is to make kids happy and at the same time sharpen their mind.

What do you think is the most important quality in a leader? Describe a time you have attempted to embody this quality when working with others.

<I hear, i forget>,< i see, i remember>,< i do, i know>. it was written next to the blackboard in our in high school chemistry class. That didn't make the class any more interesting for me, but ended up teaching me great life lesson

Thanks to my teacher, i have strong belief that knowledge comes from action. That's why i believe great quality someone can have is the ability to execute things to the best of his or her abilities especially if that person wants to be strong leader.

when i was asked to be project leader on the companies i have worked for,i tend not to limit my responsibility on setting the deadline and delegating the work, but also taking time to do the tasks with my team. I dedicate time to learn on new things and share my experience with my team

During the Fellowship, you will be exposed to new opinions and worldviews held by other Fellows and by the Americans you meet. Describe a time where you worked with people of different backgrounds, identities, or perspectives from your own. What strategies have you used in the past to navigate these situations, and what lessons have you learned from the challenges you faced?

I had the pleasure of working in us based outsourcing company. Among other things, the creative freedom i was given and the friendly communication my American boss used was completely new to me. I have always worked based on specific instruction. I had conservative and limited communication with my previous bosses.

At first i didn't know how to manage it but i know in order to to keep my job i had to change .If evolution taught us anything its nature favors individuals who adopted to new environment over the others. so I asked my seniors for help, I spent most of my time listening instead of talking.I figured out how to express myself in open yet respectful manner.

I can confidently say letting employees have creative freedom and open line of communication helps get things done in quick and efficient manner. I am looking forward to and share my experience with my future employees.

Learning from mistakes is a part of professional development, and strong leaders are able to effectively handle challenges. Describe a specific instance when you made a mistake or encountered a setback that helped you grow as a leader. What did you do and how are you applying those lessons learned in your current work?

When i started my first software company i had no vision or clear plan. I believed if i worked hard enough things will fall into right places. I had lost all my savings by the time i figured i was on the wrong track

I was struggling whether i should go back and find another job or give myself another chance. Then I noticed my father, man on his fifties struggling to take one step closer to his chair. He was diagnosed with Parkinson's disease when he was only 47. Despite his body refusing to cooperating he still does everything he used to before his diagnosis.

He is a fighter. I wanted to be like him. To succeed i know i should have clear vision and set goals. I should fight for what i want. I decided to restart everything. I come up with clear vision and plan. I partnered up with my friends and am working harder than before.

An important goal of the Fellowship is to develop skills that Fellows need to help them give back to their home communities through their professional or personal work. Describe a specific problem or challenge in your community that you have solved or are currently working to address. Explain the steps you took or are taking to address the problem. Why is this issue important to you?

Even Though Ethiopia is developing hastily, as nation we lack the tremendous benefit that could be gained from computer science based technologies. An estimated 85 percent of the population are believed to be engaged in agricultural production. Most of this farmers haven't received any formal education. Brokers and merchants in the city takes advantage of this uneducated farmers by buying the product in cheap price and selling it in the city with high profit.

As my grandparent and great grandparents were farmers. I am determined to do everything i can with my knowledge and professional skill to make sure everyone gets their fair share of the profit.

Nowadays thanks to social media and smartphones . The youth even in the rural areas can get up to date information using the

smartphone on the internet. As a technologist i wanted to take advantage of that.

I partnered up with my friends from same field and we created online shopping platform (e-commerce) and we are advertising it using social medias. Along online shopping, the online payment platform should go hand and hand we contacted other ambitious young entrepreneurs that are working on payment system and we are currently trying to come up with way on how to work together and launch our product.

We are hoping this if this young people get the right information and pass it to the farmer. we will help the community get most out of every transaction.

Based on your understanding of your preferred track, what skills and knowledge do you hope to gain from the Fellowship that you would not be able to develop through other education or training? How will you use those skills and that knowledge to adapt your activities in your home country within the next 3 – 5 years?

My biggest dream is to become a successful female entrepreneur. I want to build an innovative software company, create a job opportunity for youths in my community. I want to show my community a women can do it all. It's a matter of getting the chance and have the correct mindset.

By participating in this fellowship, am hoping to gain the skill set that will make me become a strong leader. If we want to change our community and make a difference in this world we should become problem solvers. We should learn from others. Both from the mistake and success stories. That's why i'm looking forward to share my experience and learn from the experience of other participants.

As someone who was born and raised in country with 80 nations and nationalities. Dealing with people with different background has taught me big lesson. Each experience made my communication skill grow. My view on things widen and i see the advantage and harmony difference can create.

Within the next 3- 5 years i want to be able to build multiple software solution that will helps my community. Replace labor intensive, tedious work with fast and efficient technology. I want to partner up with other young ambitious entrepreneur like me. I want to travel to rural areas in my country and teach the basics of technology. How it can make our life better.

## VI. Optional Professional Development Experience (PDE)

Would you like to apply to the Mandela Washington Fellowship internship?

Yes

and the training's i get.

What are your goals for the Professional Development Experience? How would you apply an experience working in a U.S. organization to your work after returning to your home country?

"Ideas are cheap, execution is everything." one of my favorite quote. I heard it from my favorite tech entrepreneur Mark Cuban on shark tank. I consider myself a creative person and am motivated and team player. My dream is to be successful business owner.

I know getting to my goal will not be a straight line, it will be full of challenges and problems. In order to face my challenges and overcome the obstacles i need the right technique and strategy. Am hoping to acquire this and other skills from the the organization

When i come back to Ethiopia, i want to go give back to my community by sharing this experience. I will give training, write blogs and share what i have learnt in all possible ways.

I also want to partner up with the others in different profession and come up with strategy to contextualize the teachings to fit to my culture.

I will take closer look on how Americans come to be the leader in business and technology. I want the same thing for my country. So i

I will take closer look on how Americans come to be the leader in business and technology. I want the same thing for my country. So i will pay attention on how things run there. What I can learn from it and how i can implement it here.

## VII. Previous U.S. Experience

Have you traveled to the
United States before?

No

of Exit

U.S.

Date of Entry	Date
to U.S.	from

U.S. Visa
Type (J, F, B, etc.)

Host Institution (if applicable)

Purpose of Travel (study, personal, business, etc.)

Funding Source or Sponsor (personal, US government, etc.)

## VIII. English Language

Reading	Writing	Speaking	Listening Comprehension
Excellent	Excellent	Excellent	Excellent

## IX. Resume

See formatted resume at end of document.

## X. Optional Supplemental Documents

Optional File	01.jpg
Optional File	02.jpg
Optional File	Not available

## XI. Supplemental Questions

How did you first learn	
about the Mandela	Other (A friend who have participated in previous compititon)
Washington Fellowship?	

# Fetiha Abdella

Addis Ababa, Ethiopia

#### **SUMMARY**

Fetiha kedir is a software developer with 4 years experience in the field. She is aspire to be tech entrepreneur. she admires diversity. she is open to new ideas and perspectives. she believes in partnership and team work.

She credited her parents and the society she grew up in for her success and wants to give back to her community. she is not afraid to fail . she believes failure can teach as much as success.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Bits to Bytes Jul. 2017-Jan. 2018

Full stack developer | Ethiopia, Addis Ababa

This is a startup company i have started with my colleagues, i am project manager on the projects we have

YYT Nov. 2015-Jun. 2017

Full stack developer | Ethiopia, Addis Ababa

I worked on multiple websites and web application, my development was focused on the front end side of the project

**Appdiv** Aug. 2014-Nov. 2015

junior software developer | Ethiopia, Addis Ababa

I worked on multiple web and mobile application as designer, developer and also tester, after working for while i was assigned to be a team leader.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### Addis Ababa University | Addis Ababa, Ethiopia

Oct. 2010-Jul. 2014

BS, computer sience

Receive bachelors degree on computer science form Addis Ababa University.

#### OTHER PROFESSIONAL TRAINING

## Leadership and Management skills development | Addis Ababa, Ethiopia

Mar. 2018-Jun. 2018

Took 3 month course and received leadership and Management skills development certification

#### **COMMUNITY AND VOLUNTEER WORK**

Rotract club of Lewit | Addis Ababa, Ethiopia

Jun. 2014-Jan. 2015

participate occasionally on volunteer activities and fund raising

#### **HONORS AND AWARDS**

# **Ambassadorship of Good Ethics**

May. 2017

Vision Ethiopian Congress for Democracy

Received a certificate after participating on voluntary activities like blood donation and community service

#### **SKILLS**

Generated by the IREX Online Application System on 10/9/2018 6:35 PM. Page 6.

## Languages:

- Amharic (Native speaker)
- English (Full proficiency)

## Software:

- Database design (Advanced proficiency)
- Mobile application development (Advanced proficiency)
- project management (Intermediate proficiency)
- Web and desktop application development (Advanced proficiency)
- Website development (Advanced proficiency)